<post title="Relativistic Propulsion">
  <h1>Project Valkyrie</h1>

  <p>The Project Valkyrie spacecraft was designed by Charles Pellegrino and
  James Powell, and first presented in the book Flying to Valhalla. A more
  technicaly description, similar to that in the book's afterword, was presented
  by Pellegrino in the essay <cite id="relrob">Relativistic robots and the
  feasibility of interstellar flight</cite>.

  In it, Pellegrino makes this claim:</p>

  <quote>The Valkyrie, as our rocket is called, will have a maximum cruising
  speed of 92 percent lightspeed</quote>

  <p>I have yet to see a detailed explanation of how this number was
  reached. The design of the Valkyrie, at least in the abstract, is certainly
  very promising, but I wouldn't make any specific numerical claims.

  I've bought <i>Flying to Valhalla</i>. It's one of the few books I've actually
  bought, and while I wouldn't say it's very good in its specifics, the general
  ideas make it a worthwhile read.</p>

  <h2>Design Problems</h2>

  Possibly the most obvious problem is the violation of the Golden Rule: The
  ship has two engines, one at the front and one at the back, because turning
  broadside while coasting at relativistic speeds opens the ship up to a
  disastrous impact.

  I doubt the risk would be significant, but even if it were -- Even if
  interstellar space does turn out to be a constant shower of ice crystals --
  there's simply no way to justify doubling the mass of an engine that is
  already bound to be massive.

  The solution is fairly obvious: Engine, tether, crew and cargo, in that order
  from zenith to nadir. The process of turning the engine safely would be:

  <ol>
    <li>While coasting, and when the engine is off, roll up the tether until the
    cargo is next to the engine.</li>
    <li>Eject the shielding and its power source, and vernier it a few hundreds
    of meters forward.</li>
    <li>Rotate the engine/cargo. Most of it would remain within the shadow of
    the shield, but some areas would probably be exposed to impacts (Although
    this depends on the specifics of the shielding).</li>
    <li>Attach the shielding to the cargo section.</li>
    <li>Extend the tether.</li>
    <li>Relight the engine at will.</li>
  </ol>

  <p>Note that while the ship was accelerating, the forces were those of the
  engine and those of drag from the shielding. As the ship decelerates, drag
  from the shielding will push the cargo section closer to the engine. The
  engine, then, has to run perpetually and counteract this drag so the tether
  remains taut.</p>

  <h1>Humans are Fragile</h1>

  <h2>Acceleration</h2>

  <h2>Radiation</h2>

  <h2>Life Support</h2>

  <h2>Are humans worth it?</h2>

  <p>Seen from a rather extraterrestrial perspective, the idea of sending humans
  -- canned primates -- across interstellar distances is a completely hubristic
  fantasy. At the very least there's a very sharp contrast, between animals that
  evolved to live a few decades within a couple kilometers of the tribe, and
  incredible machines that can cross the distance between stars.

  Solid state is easier. Hook it up to the tether, and it's up, up and
  away<ref id="eleitl"/>.</p>

  <h1>Propulsion</h1>

  <h2>Antimatter</h2>

  <h2>Monopole-Catalyzed Total Conversion</h2>

  <p><l id="mag">Magnetic monopoles</l> are particles that act, as their name
  implies, as magnets with a single pole. What makes them interesting, from a
  practical perspective, is that under some GUTs, monopoles trigger proton
  decay<ref id="pdecay"/> on contact. The process is essentially the same as
  pair annihilation, only <b>the monopole remains</b>. Which means it can be
  reused: Throw a stream of plasma at a group of magnetically-suspended
  monopoles, and you have a guaranteed fusion reactor.

  Magnetic monopoles are guaranteed to exist. Every school of modern physics
  agrees that they exist. They explain the quantization of electric charge and
  certain subtleties about the post-inflation early Universe I'm too simple to
  understand.

  I would like to provide here an estimation of the luminosity and diameter of
  an accelerator capable of producing stable magnetic monopoles, but that's too
  far from my grasp. "Circumstellar" seems like a good estimate of size.  As for
  the power requirements, I don't think a <l id="kardashev">civilization</l>
  that can produce monopoles has any need for them in energy
  production. However, they remain useful for two obvious purposes: Power
  generation in deep-space operations, and space propulsion.

  Fission and fusion both require particular ingredients, but protons are all
  the same, and monopoles don't discriminate.

  As an aside: We don't know the exact mass of magnetic monopoles. Estimates
  vary from $4 \times 10^4~\mathrm{GeV}$ to $10^{17}~\mathrm{GeV}$<ref
  id="monmass"/>, the latter being <cite id="preskill">comparable to the mass of
  a bacterium, or the kinetic energy of a charging rhinoceros</cite>.</p>

  <h3>Difficulties</h3>

  <sidenote>
    (Aside from, you know, <i>building a circumstellar supercollider</i>)
  </sidenote>

  <h4>Producing Magnetic Monopoles</h4>

  <p>"Build a very big accelerator" is incredibly vague. What exactly would it
  have to <i>do</i> to produce magnetic monopoles? Lindell references a
  paper<ref id="production"/> that proposes using high energy $pp$ (That's
  proton-proton) collisions to produce a monopole-antimonopole pair through
  photon fusion, but the paper is behind a paywall so I can't comment on that.

  Instead I tried to get two papers that cite it, <cite
  id="monopolium">Monopolium production from photon fusion at the Large Hadron
  Collider</cite> and <cite id="lhc">Looking for magnetic monopoles at LHC with
  diphoton events</cite>.</p>

  <h4>Stability</h4>

  <p>Monopoles, because of their nature, don't have the safety guarantees of
  nuclear fusion: A monopole-catalyzed fusion reactor may go supercritical, much
  like a fission reactor. Antimatter-catalyzed fusion has this same problem but
  to a much smaller degree: Antimatter is annihilated, monopoles remain.</p>

  <h4>Separating Monopoles from Fusion Products</h4>

  <p>We want the plasma and gamma rays from fusion to leave the exhaust, but the
  monopoles to remain, which is bound to be hard since the monopoles will be
  pushed around by the highly-energetic fusion reactions that themselves
  trigger.

  A possible solution takes advantage of the vast mass difference between a
  proton and a Grand Unification monopole: If you make both travel in an arc,
  guided by a magnetic field, the monopole will stick to its original trajectory
  more than the proton, because it has a much greater inertia. The specifics of
  this would probably be fairly complicated, and require actually knowing the
  mass of monopoles.</p>

  <h4>Monopolar Ramjets</h4>

  <p>This section is somewhat of an afterthought. In 1985, Robert Zubrin and Dana
  Andrews analyzed the Bussard fusion ramjet, and concluded that the drag
  created by protons brushing against the magnetic field is greater than the
  thrust of the engine -- by nine orders of magnitude. So much drag, in fact,
  that it inspired the idea of the <l id="magsail">magnetic sail</l>.

  It is unlikely that a fusion ramjet upgraded to use antimatter or
  monopole-catalyzed fusion will be able to overcome this gap, but the thought
  is left here.</p>

  <h1>Design</h1>

  <h2>Shielding</h2>

  <h2>Dust</h2>

  <h2>Radiation</h2>

  <h2>Tether</h2>

  <p>The tether is an important part of the spacecraft and is in a very
  vulnerable position: Sandwiched between the exhaust plumes of two engines with
  massive power outputs. Radiation from the conversion reactions and plasma from
  the plume could erode the tether over time, and heat radiatied by the plume
  and adsorbed by the tether could cause it to overheat and maybe require its
  own cooling system.

  To address this last problem, the tether should be a ribbon: Wide, flat, and
  coplanar with both engines. A ribbon exposes a smaller cross-section to the
  exhaust plumes and would adsorb less heat, as you can see in the very
  scientific image below:</p>

  <p>Specifically, a tether with radius $r$ exposes $r\pi$ of surface to each
  engine, while a tether with the same cross-sectional area as the ribbon
  ($r^2\pi$) and with a width of $10r\pi$ would only expose $r/10$. Not having
  the tether overheat removes one requirement: A vast, multi-kilometer long
  cooling system that just adds mass.</p>

  <references>
    <ref id="relrob">
      <title>Relativistic robots and the feasibility of interstellar flight</title>
      <author>Charles R. Pellegrino</author>
      <link>https://web.archive.org/web/20111116172452/http://www.charlespellegrino.com/propulsion.htm</link>
      <desc>
        The essay has since been taken down and redirects to the related essay
        <i>These New Oceans</i>, so a link to the Internet archive is provided.
      </desc>
    </ref>
    <ref id="pdecay">
      <title>Searches for Proton Decay and Superheavy Magnetic Monopoles</title>
      <author>B. V. Sreekantan</author>
      <link>http://www.ias.ac.in/jarch/jaa/5/251-271.pdf</link>
      <desc>
        <quote>Rubakov (1981) and independently Callan (1982a, b) have shown
        that the grand unification monopole, when it passes through matter, can
        induce proton decay through reactions of the type $M + p \rightarrow
        Me^+\pi^0, M\mu^+K^0, Me^+\mu^+\mu^-$ etc. The monopole would come out
        unscathed in the reaction, but would cause the break up of the proton in
        a manner identical to what happens in proton decay.</quote>
      </desc>
    </ref>
    <ref id="eleitl">
      <link>http://gnusha.org/logs/2013-01-22.log</link>
      <desc>
        <code><![CDATA[
          07:28 < eleitl> Solid state travels very lightly, especially if you
          leave the drive at home.

          07:28 < eleitl> Up to 0.9 c in mere weeks.

          07:28 < eleitl> Up, up and away.
          ]]>
        </code>
      </desc>
    </ref>
    <ref id="preskill">
      <title></title>
      <author></author>
      <link></link>
      <desc>

      </desc>
    </ref>
    <ref id="monmass">
      <title></title>
      <author></author>
      <link></link>
      <desc>

      </desc>
    </ref>
    <ref id="production">
      <title>On Production of Magnetic Monopoles Via $\gamma\gamma$ Fusion at High Energy $pp$ Collisions</title>
      <author>Yu. Kurochkin</author>
    </ref>
  </references>
  <links>
    <l id="mag" uri="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnetic_monopole"/>
    <l id="kardashev" uri="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kardashev_scale"/>
    <l id="magsail" uri="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnetic_sail"/>
  </links>
</post>
