<post title="Relativistic Propulsion">
  <h1>Project Valkyrie</h1>

  <p>The Project Valkyrie spacecraft was designed by Charles Pellegrino and
  James Powell, and first presented in the book Flying to Valhalla. A more
  technicaly description, similar to that in the book's afterword, was presented
  by Pellegrino in the essay <cite id="relrob">Relativistic robots and the
  feasibility of interstellar flight</cite>.

  In it, Pellegrino makes this claim:</p>

  <quote>The Valkyrie, as our rocket is called, will have a maximum cruising
  speed of 92 percent lightspeed</quote>

  <p>I have yet to see a detailed explanation of how this number was
  reached. The design of the Valkyrie, at least in the abstract, is certainly
  very promising, but I wouldn't make any specific numerical claims.

  I've bought <i>Flying to Valhalla</i>. It's one of the few books I've actually
  bought, and while I wouldn't say it's very good in its specifics, the general
  ideas make it a worthwhile read.</p>

  <h2>Design Problems</h2>

  Possibly the most obvious problem is the violation of the Golden Rule: The
  ship has two engines, one at the front and one at the back, because turning
  broadside while coasting at relativistic speeds opens the ship up to a
  disastrous impact.

  I doubt the risk would be significant, but even if it were -- Even if
  interstellar space does turn out to be a constant shower of ice crystals --
  there's simply no way to justify doubling the mass of an engine that is
  already bound to be massive.

  The solution is fairly obvious: Engine, tether, crew and cargo, in that order
  from zenith to nadir. The process of turning the engine safely would be:

  <ol>
    <li>While coasting, and when the engine is off, roll up the tether until the
    cargo is next to the engine.</li>
    <li>Eject the shielding and its power source, and vernier it a few hundreds
    of meters forward.</li>
    <li>Rotate the engine/cargo. Most of it would remain within the shadow of
    the shield, but some areas would probably be exposed to impacts (Although
    this depends on the specifics of the shielding).</li>
    <li>Attach the shielding to the cargo section.</li>
    <li>Extend the tether.</li>
    <li>Relight the engine at will.</li>
  </ol>

  <p>Note that while the ship was accelerating, the forces were those of the
  engine and those of drag from the shielding. As the ship decelerates, drag
  from the shielding will push the cargo section closer to the engine. The
  engine, then, has to run perpetually and counteract this drag so the tether
  remains taut.</p>
</post>
